Finding Aid for Solar Car Team (University of Michigan) records, 1985-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Solar Car Team (University of Michigan) records
1985-2009
1989-2003
University of Michigan. Solar Car Team.
921120 Bimu 2
The Solar Car Team is an interdisciplinary student organization at the University of Michigan whose objectives are to design, finance, build and race a solar-powered vehicle from scratch. The collection documents the activities and experiences of several generations of the team, including team organization, design, fundraising, construction, testing and racing.
23 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
94104 digital records 4.06 GB 52.1 MB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Solar Car Team (Donor No. 8010 ) in a series of accessions beginning in 1992.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The Solar Car records are open for research use with the exception of the Student Papers which are subject to FERPA restrictions. Also restricted are Corporate Sponsorship files from the 2008 accession.
The Solar Car record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 15 and 23
Corporate Sponsorship Records -- Boxes 20-22
In November 1987, General Motors won the Australian World Solar Challenge, a two-day solar car race on public roads testing alternative-fuel vehicles, with its vehicle Sunraycer. In July 1990, rather than building another car, GM sponsored a race of its own, GM Sunrayce USA, in which 32 North American schools drove an eleven-day route from Florida to Michigan. The top three qualifiers were partially supported by GM to compete in the November 1990 World Solar Challenge, a 1,900-mile race through Australia.
The University of Michigan Solar Car Team formed in the spring of 1989 in response to GM's request for participants, and included students of engineering, business, art and journalism. The team's entry Sunrunner, designed, built and tested in 18 months, took first place in the GM Sunrayce, earning a spot in the World Solar Challenge. The team competed against 36 cars in Australia, including those of Japanese automakers and the faculty of the Swiss Engineering School of Biel. Sunrunner placed third overall and first among American entries.
The Sunrunner team carried out administrative and technical duties. Administrative groups managed finance, logistics and publicity. Technical groups were responsible for body structure (frame, suspension and steering), chassis (driveline: wheels, hubs, tires and brakes), exterior (vehicle shell and solar collection efficiency), interior (cockpit area, instrument panel and driver controls), power electronics (control subsystem, instrumentation, and telemetry), race strategy, and solar cells.
The second-generation Solar Car Team competed against 35 other North American colleges and universities in Sunrayce USA 93, sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy. The seven-day race, held in June 1993, covered approximately 1,000 miles from Texas to Minnesota. University of Michigan's new entry Maize & Blue, finished in first place, securing the team's second national championship and the opportunity to compete again in the World Solar Challenge. The team came in 11th place out of more than 50 teams in Australia, after experiencing difficulties with Maize & Blue's solar array.
This team's structure differed from that of the original team. Students worked in eight project teams: Aerodynamics/Body, Business (Fundraising/Public Relations and Logistics/Finance), Chassis, Computers, Power Electronics, Race Strategy, Solar Cells and Systems/Engineering. Project teams were overseen by the project manager, faculty advisor and executive committee.
Development of Solar Vision began in 1993. It competed in Sunrayce 95, but was forced to withdraw after day four due to a serious accident on the road attributed to advanced technologies employed in Solar Vision's design.
The university continued its tradition of solar car racing with Wolverine, taking sixth place in Sunrayce 97; MaizeBlaze placing 17th in Sunrayce 99 and 9th place in the 1999 World Solar Challenge; M-Pulse, winning the 2001 American Solar Challenge and taking third place in the World Solar Challenge; SpectruM, was not able to compete in the 2003 American Solar Challenge or the World Solar Challenge 2003 due to mechanical problems that occurred during qualifying; Momentum, winning the 2005 North American Solar Challenge and placing third in the World Solar Challenge 2005; Continuum, which will compete in the 2007 World Solar Challenge in Australia. The tenth generation solar car Infinium 2009 was unveiled in June of 2009 and raced in the World Solar Challenge in October of 2009.
For information on the current team and its solar car, see: http://www.engin.umich.edu/solarcar/, available as of April 2009.
U of M Solar Cars
1990 Sunrunner
1993 Maize & Blue
1995 Solar Vision
1997 Wolverine
1999 MaizeBlaze
2001 M-Pulse
2003 SpectruM
2005 Momentum
2007 Continuum
2009 Infinium
The records of the various U-M Solar Car projects have been received in multiple accessions and are generally described by accession. Accessions are typically organized around specific vehicles, but do contain material carried over from previous cars and races reflecting the fact that students learned from and built on the work of previous teams. For this reason, researchers are advised to review all accessions. The records contain a wide variety of documentation on the design, building, financing and racing of the solar cars and administrative and project management records.
Records include group reports; topical files; and binders containing newsletters and bulletins, and administrative and technical information for the cars; also included are videocassettes detailing design, building, and racing of the Sunrunner solar-powered automobile; photographs and albums of snapshots of team members performing general team tasks and captures of the Solar Car Team website.
Subjects:
Automobiles.; Solar cars.; University of Michigan. Solar Car Team.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobiles.; Solar cars.; University of Michigan. Solar Car Team.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- 1992 Accession
  The 1992 Accession of records of the University of Michigan Solar Car Team (4 linear feet) dates from 1989 to 1993 and consists of Visual Materials (videos and a photo album), a series of Binders, student end-of-term Group Reports, and Topical Files (from the Solar Car Team's filing cabinet).
  There are two videos within the Visual Materials subseries. The Making of Sunrunner by George Bournias summarizes the creation of Sunrunner and details student participation in the project. The second video is actually a combination of two slide programs: Cut 1: The Sunrunner Down Under and Cut 2: USA and Australia Slide Program. The subseries also includes a photo album containing pictures of team members performing different tasks. Only a small number of the photographs in the album are labeled.
  The Binder subseries includes a set of five binders (1 linear foot) maintained by Frank E. Stagg, exterior design group leader. Covering the years 1989 and 1990, these "Sunrunner Books" contain newsletters and bulletins, lecture notes, timelines, budget and sponsor information, wind tunnel data, exterior group agendas, work schedules and weekly goals, Australia race rules and general correspondence.
  Also part of this subseries are the "Team Binders" (1 linear foot). These are arranged alphabetically by team function and also date from 1989 to 1990. These materials provide insight into the creation of Sunrunner, highlighting design concepts and testing results.
  The Group Reports subseries (1 linear foot) is also arranged alphabetically by team function. This series (dating from 1989 to 1990) includes bound and unbound reports. The level of student reporting ranges from the general "what I learned on this project" to very detailed reports with charts, graphs, and accounts of individual accomplishments.
  The Topical Files subseries (.75 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and consists primarily of materials from the solar car team office filing cabinet. Materials in this series (dating from 1989 to 1990) include lecture notes from Aero Viroment, student applications and biographies, GM Sunrayce USA and World Solar Challenge information, meeting minutes, newsletters and bulletins. Also a part of this series is information relating to a student history project completed in 2001 examining the solar car team from its beginnings in 1989. Included is their final paper and correspondence with former team members about their experiences with the project.
  - Visual Materials
    - Videocassettes (Box 1)
      - The Making of Sunrunner (produced by George Bournias) (Box 1)
        (VHS; ca. 20 min.; col.)
      - Combined video: Cut 1: The SUNRUNNER Down Under and Cut 2: USA and Australia Slide Program (produced by Michigan Engineering Television Network) (Box 1)
    - Photographs
      - Album of snapshots of team members performing general team tasks (Box 1)
  - Binders
    - "Sunrunner Books", 5 volumes (Box 1)
    - Team Binders (Box 2)
      - Body Structure (Box 2)
      - Driveline, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Exterior (Box 2)
      - Failure Modes and Effects Analysis (Box 2)
      - Forecasting (Box 2)
      - Frame Design (Box 2)
      - Interior, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Logistics (Box 2)
      - Power Electronics, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Race Strategy, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Rear Suspension Design (Box 2)
      - Solar Array (Box 3)
      - Solar Cells (Box 3)
      - Team Strategy (Box 3)
  - Group Reports
    - Administration (Box 3)
    - Body Structure, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Driveline, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Engineering (Box 3)
    - Exterior (Box 3)
    - Failure Modes and Effects Analysis (Box 3)
    - Interior (includes photographs) (Box 4)
    - Power Electronics, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Race Strategy (Box 4)
    - Solar Power, 2 folders (Box 4)
      (includes photographs)
    - Team management (Box 4)
    - Weather Forecast (Box 4)
    - Aero Viroment Lectures (Box 4)
    - Applications for Race Crew and Drivers (Box 4)
    - Completed Biographies (Box 4)
    - Fax updates (Box 4)
    - General--GM SUNRAYCE USA, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - General--World Solar Challenge-Australia (Box 4)
    - GM SUNRAYCE USA Bulletins (Box 4)
    - History project, 2001 (Box 4)
      (Alumni information gathered and paper written by history students)
    - Solar Car Team Meeting Minutes (Box 4)
    - World Solar Challenge Bulletin (Box 4)
- Accession, 1994
  The 1994 accession of the University of Michigan Solar Car Team (4.2 linear feet) date from 1985 to 1994 and consist of three subseries: Background Materials, Solar Car Team and Product Information.
  The Background Materials subseries (.2 linear feet) is divided into three subseries. The first focuses on the University of Michigan Solar Car Team. It contains brochures, a milestones summary, a team handbook and general background materials. The second file concentrates on the GM Sunrayce USA. It includes awards, brochures, newsletters and official regulations. The third file examines the World Solar Challenge. It includes general materials, newsletters and official regulations.
  The Solar Car Team subseries (3 linear feet) is divided into four files. The first focuses on the Executive Committee. It contains meeting agendas, minutes and memoranda dating from 1990 to 1992. The second subseries centers on the Faculty Advisor. It contains Bruce Karnopp's correspondence and print outs of e-mail (dating from 1991 to 1992). The third file focuses on the Project Manager. It has been divided into the files of Susan Fancy and Furqan Nareeri. Susan Fancy's files contain her correspondence from 1990 to 1991. Furqan Nazeeri's files contain correspondence, materials relating to the National Research Energy Laboratory purchase order, summer management committee, Sunrayce proposals, travel materials and miscellaneous materials. These materials date from 1989 to 1993. The fourth file (dating from 1985 to 1993) concentrates on the eight Project Teams. It is arranged alphabetically by team name. Teams include Aerodynamics/Body, Business (Fundraising/Public Relations and Logistics/Finance), Chassis, Computer, Power Electronics, Race Strategy, Solar Cells and Systems/Engineering.
  The Product Information subseries (1 linear foot) consists of information on commercial products collected by the team from 1989 to 1993. Materials are arranged alphabetically by company name.
  - Background Materials
    - U of M Solar Car Team (Box 5)
      - General, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 5)
    - GM Sunrayce USA
      - Awards, 1993 (Box 5)
      - Brochures, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Newsletters, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
      - Regulations, 1989-1994 (Box 5)
    - World Solar Challenge
      - General, 1993 (Box 5)
      - Newsletters, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 5)
      - Regulations, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Solar Car Team
    - Executive Committee
      - Agenda, Minutes and Memoranda, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Advisor
      - Bruce Karnopp
        - Correspondence and Email, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - Project Manager
      - Susan Fancy
        - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      - Furqan Nazeeri
        - Correspondence
          - General, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 5)
          - GM Sunrayce 93 Awards Ceremony and Workshop, 1992 (Box 5)
          - Sunrayce Regulations Questions, 1990-1993 (Box 5)
          - Teambuilding, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
        - NREL Purchase Order, 1992 (Box 5)
        - Summer Management Committee (Box 5)
        - Sunrayce Proposal, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
        - Travel, 1992; Undated (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous, 1989-1993; Undated (Box 5)
      - David Goodman, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Project Teams
      - Aerodynamics/Body
        - Aerodynamics Testing, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 5)
        - Articles, 1988-1991; Undated (Box 5)
        - Exterior Design Proposals, 1991; Undated (Box 5)
        - General
          - Agendas, minutes, weekly plans, tasks and project summary, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 5)
          - Brian Gabel, 1991-1993; Undated (Box 5)
          - Shawn Gabel, 1992; Undated (Box 5)
        - Improvement Proposals, Undated (Box 5)
      - Business
        - Fundraising/Public Relations
          - General
            - Dan Ross, 1990-1993; Undated (Box 5)
            - Lesley Camblin, 1992; Undated (Box 5)
          - Fundraising
            - Business Plan, 1992; Undated (Box 5)
            - Gifts in Kind, Undated (Box 5)
            - Proposals, 1991; Undated (Box 5)
            - Sponsor Files, 4 folders (Box 5)
            - Sponsor Lists, 1990-1993; Undated (Box 6)
            - Sponsorship proposals, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
            - Telemarketing, Undated (Box 6)
          - Human Resources
            - Team Biographies and Executive Committee Biosheets, 1991; Undated (Box 6)
            - New Member Information, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
            - Race Team Forms, 1993 (Box 6)
            - Team Lists, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 6)
            - Team Membership Characteristics and Resumes, Undated. (Box 6)
            - Team Meeting Agendas and Posters (Box 6)
          - Public Relations
            - Conferences, 1991 (Box 6)
            - GM Sunrayce Logo, Undated (Box 6)
            - Newsletter Mailing Lists, 1990-1992; Undated (Box 6)
            - Other Races, 1992; Undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
            - National Advisory Committee, 1991-1993; Undated (Box 6)
            - Other Competitors, 1991-1993 (Box 6)
            - Photographs, 1990; Undated (Box 6)
            - Presentations and Events
              - Correspondence, schedules and programs, 1990-1992; Undated (Box 6)
              - Presentation Materials, 1990 (Box 6)
            - Press Clippings, 1988-1993; Undated (Box 6)
            - Solar Car Specifications and Statistics, 1990-1993; Undated (Box 6)
        - Logistics/Finance
          - Accounts, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
          - Budgets, 1989-1992 (Box 6)
          - Contributions, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
          - Executive Summaries, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
          - Expenses, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 6)
          - Phone Bills, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
          - Purchasing Procedures/Guidelines, 1991; Undated (Box 6)
          - Tax Exempt Information, 1989 (Box 6)
          - Timelines, 1990; Undated (Box 6)
          - Travel Arrangements, 1993 (Box 6)
      - Chassis
        - Articles, 1985; 1989; Undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Brakes, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
        - Design, 1989-1993; Undated (Box 6)
        - General (Box 7)
          - Agendas, goals, team lists, reports and timelines, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 7)
          - Matt Brown, Undated (Box 7)
          - Jeffrey Reece, 1990-1991; Undated (Box 7)
          - Tom Rinke, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 7)
        - Purchases, 1993; Undated (Box 7)
        - Suspension, 1992-1995; Undated (Box 7)
        - Testing, 1992; Undated (Box 7)
        - Wheels, 1994; Undated (Box 7)
      - Computer
        - Computer Aided Design
          - General, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 7)
          - Unigraphics II Manual, Undated (Box 7)
        - General
          - Agendas and timelines, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
          - Kevin Cain, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 7)
          - Lance Kalleberg
            - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 7)
            - Miscellaneous, 1991; Undated (Box 7)
      - Power Electronics
        - Agendas, Minutes and Reports, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 7)
        - Batteries, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 7)
        - Cockpit, 1991-1993; Undated (Box 7)
        - Computer Programming, Undated (Box 7)
        - Datum Interfaces, 1989 (Box 7)
        - Industry Contacts, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
        - Motor, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 7)
        - Regulated Power Supply, 1989-1991; Undated (Box 7)
        - Status Reports, 1989; Undated (Box 7)
        - Telemetry, 1992; Undated (Box 7)
        - Articles, Undated (Box 7)
        - Batteries
          - Data, 1992-1993; 3 folders (Box 7)
          - Data, 1994-1995; Undated (Box 7)
          - Data, 1997 (Box 7)
          - Printed materials, 1981-1992; Undated (Box 8)
          - Igor Rozenblit, 1994-1995 (Box 8)
        - Computer Information, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 8)
        - Crew and Drivers, 1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Meeting Agendas, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Memoranda, Team List, Race Plan, Timelines, 1990-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Meteorology, 1986-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Monitoring Equipment, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Motor and Controller Specifications, 1993; Undated (Box 8)
        - Race Route Equipment, 1989-1993; Undated (Box 8)
        - Race Route Survey, 1990-1993 (Box 8)
        - Race Trailer, Undated (Box 8)
        - Sunrayce Regional Qualifiers, 1993 (Box 8)
        - Andrew Walberer, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
      - Solar Cells
        - Articles, 1987-1988; Undated (Box 8)
        - Cell Attachment, 1990; Undated (Box 8)
        - Cell Layout, 1989-1991; Undated (Box 8)
        - Cell Purchasing, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - General, 1989-1992; Undated (Box 8)
      - Systems/Engineering
        - Agendas, Minutes, Timelines, Misc., 1991-1992; Undated (Box 8)
        - Reports, 1990; Undated (Box 8)
        - Vehicle Systems Inventory, Undated (Box 8)
  - Product Information
    - AC Delco (Box 8)
    - Altus Technacell (Box 8)
    - American Aerospace Controls Inc. (Box 8)
    - AMP (Box 8)
    - Anderson Power Products (Box 8)
    - Angstrohm Precision (Box 8)
    - ARCO Solar Inc. (Box 8)
    - Australian Energy Research Laboratories (Box 8)
    - Austron Inc. (Box 8)
    - Automatic Timing and Controls Company Inc. (Box 8)
    - Buckeye Stamping Co. (Box 8)
    - Carron and Company (Box 8)
    - CGS Thermodynamics (Box 8)
    - Cimatron Ltd. (Box 8)
    - Cisigraph (Box 8)
    - Control Data Corporation (Box 8)
    - Cyanamid (Box 8)
    - Dassault Systems (Box 8)
    - Eagle Picher (Box 8)
    - Electrosource (Box 8)
    - Electroswitch (Box 9)
    - In Focus Systems, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Kenwood (Box 9)
    - Kepner Tregoe (Box 9)
    - KIA Motors (Box 9)
    - Kipp and Zonen (Box 9)
    - LMS International (Box 9)
    - Magellan (Box 9)
    - Materials Property Data Network (Box 9)
    - Mettler Instrument Corporation (Box 9)
    - Moog (Box 9)
    - Parametric Technology Corporation (Box 9)
    - Patran (Box 9)
    - PDA Engineering (Box 9)
    - Photo Voltaic Yellow Pages (Box 9)
    - Photron (Box 9)
    - PI Research (Box 9)
    - Quantum Composites, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Rand Technologies (Box 9)
    - Remtron (Box 9)
    - REN Plastics (Box 9)
    - RM Young Co. (Box 9)
    - Robotic Guard Systems, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Rotocon (Box 9)
    - SAE International (Box 9)
    - Sanyo (Box 9)
    - Sharp (Box 9)
    - Silicon Sensors (Box 9)
    - Silonex Inc. (Box 9)
    - Smith Systems Inc. (Box 9)
    - Steelcase Inc. (Box 9)
    - Tool and Accessory Co. (Box 9)
    - TASC (Box 9)
    - Taskem Corporation (Box 9)
    - Thermo Sensors Corporation (Box 9)
    - Thermocouple Technology, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Thermo/Probes, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Trace Engineering (Box 9)
    - Trimble Navigation (Box 9)
    - Tudor Technology, Inc. (Box 9)
    - Unigraphics (Box 9)
    - Unique Mobility Inc. (Box 9)
    - United Solar System Corp. (Box 9)
    - U.S. Polymeric (Box 9)
    - Westinghouse Electric Systems (Box 9)
    - Williams Mobile Offices (Box 9)
- 2000 & 2001 Accessions
  The accession of files covering additions received between 2000-2001, is arranged in eight subseries, one of Visual Materials; six others by project name: Sunrunner (1990), Maize & Blue (1993), Solar Vision (1995), Wolverine (1997), MaizeBlaze (1999) and M-Pulse (2001); and the team's Website as captured in 2000. In some cases, documentation received in these accessions overlaps with prior accessions. For example, additional material on Sunrunner and Maize & Blue extends what is found in prior subseries and accessions.
  Visual Materials subseries (1.4 linear feet) include videocassettes from the first three car projects (Sunrunner, Maize & Blue and Solar Vision) as well as photographs of Solar Vision and Sunrayce 95. Sunrunner videos show construction of the vehicle and the team in the winner's circle at Sunrayce USA. A subseries of five tapes documents a visit by George Ettenheim, director of Sunrayce USA and member of General Motor's Sunraycer team, who met with the Sunrunner team to discuss strategy and planning for the race in Australia. Maize & Blue videos include both unedited tape of construction and testing of the car and surveys of the race route as well as edited footage about the project and the race itself. Solar Vision videos include professionally edited tapes of Sunrayce 95 and its results and a selection of tapes containing footage of the race route during the race. Photographs of this vehicle document construction of Solar Vision, scrutineering, qualifying runs and the race itself.
  Sunrunner (1990) subseries (1 linear foot) contains correspondence with sponsors, supporters, Sunrayce officials and others as well as general information about the vehicle's design and members of the team. Group files include, for the most part, agendas and timelines not found in previous accessions as well as some design information. Also of interest in this subseries are files relating to both Sunrayce USA and the World Solar Challenge, including pre-race preparations, updates on race progress and memorabilia.